### Curriculum Vitae – Fred Walyaula

#### Personal Profile

A seasoned Community Development Specialist, an Agro-Ecological Champion, Orphans and vulnerable persons advocate, an Environmental Social and Governance implementer with more than 10 years of experience working with several Local Governments, multinational and indigenous Organizations. I am passionate about One Health strategies to achieve Community-led development interventions through community collective actions and agroecological and social economic platforms, community SACCO formation, grants management, community capacity cascading trainings, market research and linkages. I have excellent skills in critical decision-making, evidence-based interventions, analytics, surveillance, public-speaking, research and advocacy.

#### **Formal Education**

- Master of
   Development
   Practice (MDP),
   Regis University
   Denver Colorado
   USA 2020.
- Bachelor's Degree in Social Work and Social Administration, Uganda Christian University 2006
- Diploma in Community Development, Nsamizi Training Institute for Social Development 2001

# Professional Certification and training

- Certificate in Biointensive
   Agriculture and
   Entrepreneurship Manor House
   Agricultural
   Training Center –
   Kitale Kenya 2014
- Value Chain Analysis, Business incubation and Market Research –

#### **Address**

C/O aBi Development Limited Umoja House, 2<sup>nd</sup> Floor Plot 20, Nakasero Road Kampala (U) **Email:** fredwalyaula@gmail.com | Mobile: +256 772 883 867

#### **Employment Record**

Value Chain Development and Community Engagement Technical Consultant - Share An Opportunity Uganda in Karamoja and Teso Sub-region April to October 2023

This was a short term engagement which ran from April 2023 and accomplished in October 2023.

Carried out Value chain Research and adevelopment, Rapid Market assessments, stakeholder engagements, Building capacity and monitoring of Grantee agencies, business planning, technical skills training in Gender participation, Communication, group dynamics, Business planning and enterprise development and management along different value chains.

Value Chain Development (VCD) Short Term Technical Consultant - Agriculture Business Initiative (aBi) Limited July 2022 to March 2023

This was a short-term Consultancy to oversee the implementation of 5 designated projects with aBi Implementing Partners, ensuring that good practices in end-to-end project management is adhered to and that interventions are made as required by the company Policies, within the available budgets and timelines to ensure that planned results are achieved. I concluded this Consultancy in March 2023.

- Conducted Monitoring and Validation field visits to 5 implementing partners following the set Key Performance Indicators
- ❖ Carried out end of project Evaluation for 2 projects
- Designed and contracted 5 companies and 2 farmer Organizations under the aBi Green Challenge Funding window 2022 -2023
- ❖ Inducted and trained 5 newly on boarded Companies and 2 Farmer Organization

- FCI Headquarters Nairobi Kenya 2018
- TOT Certificate in ECCD - Health Manpower Development Centre - Mbale 2003
- Certificate in Strategic Planning -St. Andrews Community Centre 2003
- TOT Certificate in Psycho-social Support to OVCs – Conducted at Soroti flying School. 2017
- Certificate in Mindset Change for sustainable Transformation course. C.I.M Center, Yatta, Machakos Kenya 2019
- **Areas of Expertise**
- Critical analysis of Socio – Economic aspects, which affect development of communities.
- Ability to coordinate and liaise with Development partners and engage value chain actors and supporters to build synergies towards community livelihood

- Implementing Partner agencies on aBi policies and procedures under the Green Challenge Fund
- Prepared and presented monthly activity plans and reports during the consultancy period.
- ❖ Developed Key Performance Indicators for newly contracted Implementing Partners embedding Climate Change, sustainability, and human rights considerations in the course of project implementation along the different value chains.

**Value Chain Development and Marketing Specialist** – Self Help Africa July 2021 to Dec 2021

My six months engagement with Self Help Africa was to develop sustainable and profitable production and marketing strategies for honey Agri-enterprises in the Karamoja and Lango sub-regions.

- ❖ Provided management oversight to 14 honey aggregation hubs, 12 cooperatives, and 15 producer groups) to improve the competitiveness of beekeepers to respond to new and expanding market opportunities.
- ❖ Conducted 45 monitoring visits to the 12 honey producing Cooperatives and 30 farmer groups in 5 Districts (Nakapiripirit, Amudat (Karamoja sub-region), Kitgum/. and Lamwo (Lango sub-region) to ensure project activities are fast tracked and provided them technical assistance according to the Self-Help Africa approved work plans.
- Linked the 12 honey producers and aggregators to two off takers i.e., Golden Bees Uganda Limited and Bee Natural who deal directly with the honey producers.

**Program Manager -** Agricultural Cooperatives and smart village women and youth led Solar power project with Africa Development Promise (ADP - Uganda) Feb 2020 to Feb 2021.

- ❖ Built capacity of 165 leaders from 25 Cooperatives engaged in different value chains through needs assessment and training.
- Linked 9 Epaphroditus Cooperative women mushroom growing groups to a Partner Organization called All Things are Possible (ALTAP) who have supported in mushroom production and value addition which has resulted into increased production and are now into collective marketing.
- ❖ Identified and assessed 24 mushrooms out growers which is a step towards increasing mushroom production.
- ❖ Identified 8 new Cooperatives in Kasangati town council which have been fully assessed and working under the guidance of Africa Development Promise in vegetable production and coffee Nursery development, coffee growing and processing respectively.
- ❖ Kasangati Town Council in November 2020 picked on Africa Development Promise as a representative of NGOs to the Town Council Technical Planning Committee which meets every Tuesday of the week. This helped in raising the profile of ADP work and the cooperatives the Organization supports.
- ❖ Facilitated the process of registering ADP with Participatory Ecological Land Use Management (PELUM) Uganda, an organization that has brought together over 59 Organizations with Climate Resilient components, offering trainings in Agro ecological production, value addition, advocacy, and marketing for small holder

- programs.
- Stakeholder mapping, analysis, and engagement.
- Human and financial resource mobilization
- Report writing and presentation.
- High facilitation skills using participatory approaches.
- Facilitating Public Policy, Governance and Regulatory Compliance
- Public administration
- Project design, implementation, and review
- Research skills
- Partnership Development
- Budget Planning &Forecasting
- Performance management & measurement
- Team Building and Motivation
- Records management
- Management Skills

# **Computer Software Packages**

- Microsoft Office
- Power point
- Excel
- Internet related programs

#### **Interests/Hobbies**

• Community mobilization and

- farmers.
- Onboarded Master Card Foundation to engage 25 ADP Cooperatives in Financial Literacy training and credit access under the Rural and Agricultural Finance Program.
- ❖ Worked with two Cooperatives, one which is into cereals and the other producing vegetables on a commercial level who are set to receive irrigation equipment with support from ADP and the Government of Uganda to overcome the challenge of rain fed production.
- ❖ We planned for a Christmas Solar energy product promotion week for the two kiosks to clear up the products in stock. This successfully took place from 14<sup>th</sup> to 17<sup>th</sup> of December 2020 and all stock was sold out.
- ❖ Coordinated field arrangements and prepared Cooperatives and solar kiosks for the Donor/ Partner/ volunteer visits which take place every 3<sup>rd</sup> Month of the year.

Markets and Trade Manager (Central, Busoga, Teso and Karamoja Sub-regions) - Farm Concern International from March 2016 to December 2019.

I joined FCI in March 2016 to December 2019. Under this docket I was responsible for Developing Quarterly and monthly work plans and Budgets, generating Programmatic reports on weekly,

Monthly, quarterly, and annual basis for FCI, Partners and Donors.

- ❖ Developed tools and carried out Market Research, Value Chain Analysis, and facilitating market Linkages between farmers for different crop and animal value chains to both formal and informal markets and Exporting companies dealing in Cereals, Horticulture, fruits, and Livestock.
- Supervised 9 Grantee Organizations, ensuring accountabilities are submitted in a timely manner and requested funds disbursed on schedule.
- Oversaw 46 Commercial Village Trade Facilitators and 8 Markets Trade Facilitators (Front line staff).
- ❖ Conducted market research/Value chain Analyses and Monitoring of Market trends for 15 FCI Partner Organization in Uganda.
- ❖ Facilitated 115 Value Chain Business Forums
- Conducted Capacity Building sessions for 118 Small Holder Farmer Groups and 39 Cooperatives
- ❖ Developing periodic work plans and business models with the 118 small holder farmer groups and 39 cooperatives under Farm Concern International.

**Agribusiness Coach** with CARD Uganda for a 10-month Consultancy job slot under the Rice Value Chain in Pallisa, Budaka and Kibuku Districts from May 2015 – Feb 2016.

Before joining Farm Concern International I worked with a Consultancy firm called Consultancy for Agribusiness and Rural Development (CARD) Uganda as an Agribusiness Coach.

- ❖ I Facilitated 10,680 rice farmers in Pallisa, Kibuku and Budaka Districts to apply Agro-ecological approaches to produce and market rice in groups.
- Trained them in group dynamics, Farming as a Business (FaaB), bulking and

capacity building of small holder farmers using participatory methods and collective actions like group formation, enterprise selection, access to inputs, production, postharvest management, bulking, marketing and management of proceeds and plough back towards sustainable development.

- Working with youth, women and other vulnerable groups towards household food security and Nutrition, social protection and rights, financial inclusion, and stakeholder engagement.
- Presiding over events and other Management practices

#### **Languages Spoken**

Official – English Local – Lumasaba and Luganda Others- Lugwere and Kiswahili

## <u>Professional Referee's</u> Sherina Munyana

- collective marketing.
- ❖ 356 Farmer groups registered at the District as Community Based Organizations (CBOs). They do rice Bulking and collective marketing.
- ❖ Linked Rice farmer Cooperatives to milling Companies like Upland Rice Millers in Jinja and Eastern Millers in Tororo, where bulked rice is milled, and good market sought.
- ❖ Farmer groups underwent Accumulated Savings and Lending Association Training, and they started group savings.
- ❖ At the end of the 10 months engagement, they had two well established and vibrant SACCOs with a tune of UGX 24,000,000/= and UGX 13,000,000/= respectively.

**Community Development Facilitator** with World Vision Uganda Mpigi Cluster–Nov 2013 to Nov 2014.

This was a 1-year Contractual engagement with World Vision Uganda – Mpigi Cluster as a Community Development Facilitator (CDF)

- ❖ Coordinated and presided over 15 commercialization events (10 Village Business Forums and 5 District level marketplace events.
- ❖ Built capacity of 62 formed Community Farmer Groups and 28 Village Savings and Loan Associations under the Long-Term Investment for Food and Economic Empowerment (LIFE) Project.
- ❖ Linked 1,860 the farmers to input dealers, Agricultural extension workers, traders, and processors.
- ❖ Developed workable and evidence-based results management frameworks with clear Key Performance Indicators (KPIs) for the LIFE Project which was later adopted for other Livelihood projects under World Vision Uganda.

**Assistant Program Officer** - The Hunger Project Uganda 22<sup>nd</sup> April 2008 – To December 2012

While with The Hunger project Uganda I was responsible for overseeing community mobilization of locally available resources to construct the Epicenter facility in Partnership with Mbale District Local Government and there after went into the day today implementation of the different Catalytic Programs.

- ❖ The Epicenter facility was constructed comprising of a Community Food store, demonstration garden, Tree nursery beds, Epicenter hall for trainings and other social events, Village Bank, Early Childhood Care center, Health facility and Health staff house.
- ❖ Spearheaded 8 Epicenter catalytic Programs including; Food Production, Food Security and Nutrition, Epicenter Income Generating Projects, Water, Sanitation and Environmental awareness building, creation and training, HIV/AIDS and Gender Inequality Program, Functional Adult Literacy Program (FAL) and Early Childhood Education, Establishing a Rural Bank Facility through group formation, training and Enterprise Selection under The Microfinance Program.
- Worked with the District Health Office to equip, stock and staff the Health unit at the Epicenter, working with partner organizations to fight malaria and other sicknesses in the community.

Country Director
Africa Development
Promise
TEL: +256 772
632466, +256
702632466
smunyana@africadevel
opmentpromise.org

#### **Tomson Okot Chono**

Former Senior Programs Manager, Farm Concern International, Uganda Team Leader. TEL: +256 704669417, +256 772669417

#### **Ronald Wabwire**

Ag. Head, Portfolio Development aBi Development Limited Umoja House, 2<sup>nd</sup> floor. Plot 20, Nakasero Road Kampala Uganda Tel: +256(0)772649012

Ronald.Wabwire@abi.

Email:

co.ug

❖ Mbale Epicenter has been ranked number one towards self-reliance with the capacity of the leaders built, Income Generating Activities.

- ❖ Partnered with National Agriculture Research Organization (NARO) under Buginyanya Zonal Agriculture Research and Development Institute where there is an improved seed multiplication project at Mbale Epicenter.
- ❖ Offered the Epicenter Hall in Mbale as a training center for Village Health Teams conducted by Malaria Consortium in Bungokho South Constituency.
- ❖ Partnered with Techno Serve, where we engaged community youth in Passion fruit and other tree seedling Nursery establishment and management as a business and establishment of water shades and woodlots.
- ❖ Was a Partnership liaison team lead for the Eastern Region Market Place Event which successfully took place on the 23<sup>rd</sup> of May 2012 in Mbale. The purpose of the event was to link individual farmers, farmer groups, input dealers, Agro processors and financial institutions in Eastern Uganda to share information and make deals to increase and improve productivity. This involved many Organizations like aBi Trust, World Vision, The Hunger Project Uganda, VECO East Africa, Techno Serve, Clear Uganda, and CARD Uganda, Share an Opportunity (SAO), Eastern Private Sector Development Center, Microfinance Institutions and Banks.

**Livelihoods Coordinator and Community Development Worker** with Christian Children's Fund – CCF, (current- Child Fund International) November 2001 to October 2007

In my tenure, I was a Community Development Worker in the affiliate Projects and later in 2006, was promoted to the position of Livelihoods Coordinator at the Area Coordination Office.

- Spearheaded development of Livelihoods Information Education and Communication materials and compiled livelihood success stories from the Farmer Field Schools through Documentaries for CCF Mbale Area Federation.
- ❖ Established 10 Farmer Field Schools with Technical support from Agriculture extension staff in partnership with Africa 2000 Network.
- Conducted 56 Nutrition Campaigns for mothers and care givers in the 10 established ECCD centers.
- Took part in the review and streamlining of the Orphans and Vulnerable Children Policy held at Soroti Flying School in 2006.
- ❖ Wrote several proposals geared towards enhancing livelihood activities in the 10 Project units in Mbale area. In 2005, we received additional funds to provide every producer farmer group with two oxen and an ox-plough.
- ❖ Attached 500 youth (50 from every Project unit) to different Vocational Institutions for Skills training in Agriculture, Carpentry, Tailoring, Brick lying and Concrete Practice, Catering, plumbing, fashion and design, hair dressing and salon. We also provided start up tools to the youth on graduation in Partnership with GTZ − a Germany Development agency.

#### **Career Milestones**

- ❖ Grant winner of USD 80,000 in 2005 to provide 70 farmer groups in Greater Mbale with two oxen and an ox-plough.
- ❖ Lead Consultant in developing the Agro ecological rice value-chain model among 10,680 rice farmers in Pallisa, Kibuku and Budaka Districts under CARD (U)

- funded by International Fertilizer Development Centre
- ❖ Team lead in drafting the PELUM Uganda's Pesa Agro-Enterprise Marketing Model.
- ❖ Received an accolade and certificate as employee of the year Farm Concern International (FCI) 2017
- ❖ Country Head of monitoring of the implementation of PELUM Uganda's Pesa Agro-Enterprise Marketing Model in the 59-member organizations.
- ❖ Led the registration of 356 Farmer groups in as Community Based Organizations (CBOs) in Eastern Uganda.
- ❖ Led a youth livelihood vocational skills program covering Agroforestry, Carpentry, Tailoring, Brick lying and Concrete Practice, Catering, plumbing, fashion and design, hair dressing. We attached 500 youths to different vocational institutions in Partnership with GTZ in Eastern Uganda. They received start up tool kits at their Graduation to gain from the skills attained.